About This Document
Prev  |   |

About This Document

Copyrights
About the Author
Acknowledgements

Copyrights

This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 2.5 License (or at your option a greater version of it). The CC-Attribution is almost Public Domain except for a requirement to make an attribution to the original author.

It was written by Shlomi Fish who also holds the copyrights.

About the Author

Shlomi Fish was born in Israel in 1977, and has lived there most of his life. He is a user, developer, advocate and activist of Open Source Software. His greatest single contribution so far in this area has been Freecell Solver, a Public Domain Library for solving games of Freecell and other types of Solitaire. However, he also initiated several other projects and made important contributions to projects he did not initiate some of them very large scale. Recently, most of his contribution were perl distributions he uploaded to CPAN under his username.

Fish's work on Freecell Solver and other open source projects, and the fact he is interested in many software management techniques has led him to write a large number of articles, and weblog entries which describe his unique views as a developer of mostly portable software.

Acknowledgements

Thanks to Mr. Gary Campbell, the author of "FCELL.COM" whose original message provided the inspiration for this article. Thanks to Omer Zak, who went over an early draft of this article and supplied many useful comments. Thanks to many people on the IRC (= Internet Relay Chat) who have read the article and comments, and chose not to be explicitly credited.

Finally, thanks to all the past and present people who helped me with Freecell Solver, and with the rest of my "Free and Open Source Software" (= FOSS) endeavours.

Prev  |   |
Analysis of the Quality of the Various Freecell Solvers  | Home |

Analysis of the Quality of the Various Freecell Solvers
Prev  |   |  Next

Analysis of the Quality of the Various Freecell Solvers

Introduction
The Analysis Itself
Conclusion

Introduction

As you recall, Gary Campbell's comment provided the motivation for my investigation into what makes a project high-quality and which quality-increasing-measures are not elements of quality by themselves. And since Freecell Solver has been my pet project, and as I'm still interested in techniques for solving Solitaire, I'd like to conclude this essay by analysing the various solvers according to the parameters I described. The natural caveat is that due to the fact I authored a solver of my own, then I may be a bit biased.

I was not so sure including this section is a good idea, but I feel the article is incomplete without it. Feel free to skip it, in case you are not that interested in it.

The Analysis Itself

As is not uncommon in many software niches, some Freecell solvers are not commonly available for downloading or even for buying. For example, Bill Raymond's solver (named "Cat in the Sack") which he has been talking about extensively, has not been released yet, under any licensing terms. Similarly, Danny A. Jones has kept his solver (mentioned in the introduction) for himself, and has not released it to the wild in either source or binary forms.

As such, the utility of such solvers is heavily reduced. For once, they cannot be used as integrated solvers of Solitaire apps, because no one is going to wait for an email to the author to be sent, and the author to reply with the solution. Also, many researchers won't trust solutions given by them without the ability to inspect the source code.

Most other solvers are available for free download, and many are accompanied with the source, most probably under an open-source licence.

Gary Campbell's Solver is written in 8086 Assembly, with some 32-bit extensions, and only runs on DOS and DOS-compatible platforms. The assembly is compiled using a self-hosting macro assembler written by Campbell. The Assembly source code of the solver or the assembler are not available. As such modifying the code of the executable may prove to be problematic.

It is tempting to think that x86 and DOS are a very low common denominator, but that is not always the case. Imagine that you are writing a Freecell game for an embedded device running a non-x86 architecture such as ARM or PowerPC. In that case, in order to run Campbell's solver, you'll need to embed an x86-and-DOS emulator (such as DOSBox) inside the device, which will complicate things, consume a lot of memory, and slow things down. On the other, a C-based solver, such as Freecell Solver, or Tom Holroyd's Patsolve, can be easily made to compile and run there with few if any modifications. So they would be preferable.

Similarly, when writing portable programs for the various Unix flavours and other POSIX-capable or C-capable operating-systems, then writing code in x86 Assembly exclusively will make it a non-starter. [Assembly]

Some Freecell solvers also don't build out of the box. For example, typing make inside the patsolve distribution yields the following output:

shlomi:~/patsolve-3.0$ make
make clean
make[1]: Entering directory `/home/shlomi/patsolve-3.0'
rm -f patsolve *.o param.c param.h core win .depend
make[1]: Leaving directory `/home/shlomi/patsolve-3.0'
touch .depend
param.py param.dat
make: param.py: Command not found
make: *** [param.h] Error 127

        

This is relatively easy to fix, but still frustrating. Freecell Solver on the other hand, has been fully converted to the GNU Autotools, and can be built as a static and shared library (a.k.a DLL), as well as several proof-of-concept, but still usable, command line utilities that link against it.

Freecell Solver has very good usability: it mostly respects the Unix conventions and best practices, it can start solving from any arbitrary Solitaire board position given to it as input, and has kept command line interface usability in mind. Campbell's solver on the other hand, as of this writing, does not operate on a standard input/standard output manner, is poorly documented, and is counter-intuitive for someone who is used to Unix conventions (and most DOS conventions). I'm not even sure it can accept any arbitrary board as input, but I may be wrong.

Regarding the homepage of the solver: the Freecell Solver homepage has many pages, a navigation menu, a common look-and-feel and many links and information. On the other hand, Patsolve is nothing but a link in Tom Holroyd's software archive, which can easily be missed. Gary Campbell's homepage for his solver has a Baroque design and quite a lot of marketing-speak. And it's only one page with no anchors or a navigation menu, and very few links. Most other solvers don't fare better than that, and certainly worse than my own.

Licensing, a necessary, but important, evil. The Freecell Solver's C source is distributed under the Public Domain licence, which allows virtually any use, including linking, modifying and sublicensing under any different licence by a third party.[PD-LICENSE] On the other hand, Patsolve is distributed under the GPL licence which while usable is considerably more restrictive than Public Domain, or BSD-style licences. This is also the case for this Common Lisp solver. Many other solvers, including Campbell's are binary-only, "All Rights Reserved", which makes them a complete no-starter for most open-source applications out there. Furthermore, many non-open-source applications will prefer to use a Public Domain solver, rather than paying royalties or risking "copyrights" and source availability problems.

Freecell Solver (FCS) is extensively documented, and even its online help is helpful and usable by itself. The other solvers are much less documented, but arguably they also have much fewer options and features than Freecell Solver does.

Which brings us to the features - Freecell Solver has a long list of features, and I'm not aware of any solver with so many of them. Especially of note is that it can solve many other Solitaire variants, including Simple Simon, of which FCS is probably the only solver capable of solving.

Most of the solvers out there are fast, but some are more than others. Normally, for solving an individual game on the command-line, almost any solver will do, and the only cases where such speed matters more is for Solitaire research, and for analysing large sets of different games. (see the Freecell FAQ for more information).

Conclusion

All things considered, I still feel that Freecell Solver is probably the best quality Solitaire solver out there. While it still has a lot of room for improvement, the rest of its competition have much bigger issues, or have not been made available (yet or ever).

Several factors contributed for its success: the fact that I announced many releases on Freshmeat.net, that I received a lot of input from my users and co-developers, that I was determined to constantly improve it and work on it, and that I worked on creating and maintaining a good web-site and documentation.

While most of the contributions of code I received were limited, the input from the users of the software proved to be crucial for its prosperity. Like I noted earlier, I lost interest in working on it (at least temporarily), but still maintain it, and feel that it is good enough as it is.

I hope this document, and similar resources it referenced will help you in working on your software, and improving its quality for the benefit of your users and you.

Happy Hacking!

[Assembly] In some cases, the developers of portable software maintain versions of parts of the code in Assembly of selected architectures, while keeping more portable versions written in C or C++. This is done to optimise some parts for common CPU architectures.

[PD-LICENSE] As noted earlier, a Public Domain non-licence has some problems, which may make the software problematic for many corporations and in some jurisdictions. However, I don't have problem in exempting the licence of the Freecell Solver code (at least not the Public Domain code that I fully originated), from the Public Domain, including under the MIT X11 Licence, assuming this is necessary.

I'm also considering relicensing Freecell Solver and other older software of mine under the MIT X11 licence, or possibly having a dual-Public Domain and MIT X11 licensing terms (which seems somewhat silly, but may be a good idea.)

Prev  |   |  Next
Ways to Achieve Quality  | Home |  About This Document

Ways to Achieve Quality
Prev  |   |  Next

Ways to Achieve Quality

Having Modular, Well-Written Code
Automated Tests
Beta Testers
Frequency of Releases
Good Software Management
Good Social Engineering Skills
No Bad Politics
Good Communication Skills
Hype
A Good Name
Conclusion

Now that we've covered the elements that make programs high-quality here's a non-exhaustive list of ways to actually achieve it. None of them are absolutely necessary for achieving the quality, but they certainly help a lot.

Many people often confuse them with quality. "This software has God-damn awful code, so it's a pile-of-crap." Well, what do the users care how bad the code is, as long as it is functional, has all the necessary features, and is (mostly) bug-free? It's important not to confuse quality with the ways to achieve it.

The aim of this section is to briefly cover as many measures for achieving good quality as possible.

Having Modular, Well-Written Code

The more modular a project's code is, the easier it is to change it, understand it and extend it, and the faster development will take. Refactoring is the name given to the process used to transform code from sub-optimal and "ugly", but still mostly functional and bug-free code, to a code that is equally functional but more modular and clean. See the "Joel on Software" excellent article "Rub a dub dub" for some of the motivation and practices of good refactoring instead of throwing away the code and restarting from scratch.

Automated Tests

Automated tests aim to test the behaviour of code automatically, instead of manual testing. The classical example for them is that if we wish to write a function called add(i, j) that aims to add two integers then we should check that add(2, 3) == 5, that add(2, 0) == 2, that add(0, 2) == 2, that add(5, -2) == 3, that add(10, -24) == -14, etc.

Then we can run all the tests and if any of them failed, we can fix them. Then after we write or modify the code, we can test using them again to see if there are any regressions.

Writing automated tests before we write the actual code, or before we fix a bug, and accumulating such tests (the so-called "Test-driven development" paradigm), is a good practice which helps maintain a high-quality software, and facilitates refactoring and makes it safer.

Beta Testers

If you have beta testers for the code, or publish development versions frequently, you can get a lot of feedback for various different platforms and configurations your code is running on. These beta-testers can run the automated tests and also use the beta-code for their own testing or even production.

Frequency of Releases

The more frequent your releases are, the more people can test your code, and the more they can upgrade to the latest version, and the quicker bugs that disturb your users are fixed, etc.

Naturally, there are advantages for slower release cycles, or for predictable release cycles like GNOME 2.x has. I won't voice a definite opinion for which is the best methodology, but such a decision should be taken into consideration.

Good Software Management

There are several sources online and offline explaining good software management for "shrinkwrap" software (open-source, commercial or other distributed) and for other types of software development (embedded, in-house, etc.), from which good advice can be taken for how to best run a software project. While the are sometimes contradictory, and often false, they still make a good read and are thought-provoking.

Here are some links:

Eric Raymond's "The Cathedral and the Bazaar" series

The "Joel on Software" site

Paul Graham's Essays (on various topics)

Extreme Programming

Good Social Engineering Skills

It certainly helps for the project's communities to have good social engineering skills. From tactfulness, to humour, to controlling one's temper, to saying "Thanks" and congratulating people for their contribution, to timely applying patches and fixing bugs - all of these makes contributing to a project and using the program more fun and less frustrating.

Often, social engineering should be made part of the design of the software, or the web-sites dedicated to it. For example, it took me several iterations of having to fill the same project form in the GNU Savannah software-hub, only for it to be rejected, and me having to follow the process again. Despite the fact the admins were polite, it still was annoying.

Eventually, they implemented a way to save previous project submissions and to re-send them, so future users won't become as frustrated as I did.

Again, some projects have succeeded despite the fact they had, or even still have, bad social engineering. But adopting a good software engineering policy can certainly help a lot.

No Bad Politics

Bad politics in a software project is a lot like subjectivity, it can never be fully eliminated, but we should still strive to reduce it to the minimum.. If bad political processes become common in a project, then important features are dropped, bugs are left unfixed, patches are stalled, external projects gets stalled or are killed, people become frustrated or angry and possibly leave the project - and the project may risk forking.

So it's a good idea to keep bad politics at bay and to a minimum. How to do that is out of the scope of the document, but it's usually up to the leaders to keep it so and maintain a good policy that will make as few people as possible frustrated and will not flabbergast external contributors. And naturally, for open-source and similar projects, a fork is often an option in this case, or in other similar cases.

Good Communication Skills

A project leader and other participants should have good communication skills: very good English; pleasantness and tact; good phrasing, proper grammar, syntax, phrasing and capitalisation; clear writing; patience and tolerance; etc. If he doesn't, then the project may encounter problems as people will find the project's developers hard to understand or tolerate, and, thus, hard to work with.

Hype

Despite common belief I believe that the less hype and general noise there is regarding a software project, the better off it is. For example, as Paul Graham notes regarding Java:

[Java] has been so energetically hyped. Real standards don't have to be promoted. No one had to promote C, or Unix, or HTML. A real standard tends to be already established by the time most people hear about it. On the hacker radar screen, Perl is as big as Java, or bigger, just on the strength of its own merits.

In fact, I can argue that if your project receives a lot of negative hype, then it is an indication that it is successful. Perl, for example, has received (and still receives) a lot of criticism, and Perl aficionados often get tired of constantly hearing or seeing the same repetitive and tired arguments by its opponents. However, the perl 5 interpreter is in good shape, it has many automated tests (much more than most other competing dynamic languages), an active community, many modules on CPAN ( the Comprehensive Perl Archive Network) with a lot of third-party , open-source functionality, and relatively few critical bugs. It is still heavily actively used and has many fans.

Similar criticism has been voiced against the Subversion version control system, Linux, etc. One thing one can notice about such highly-criticised projects is that they tend not to be bothered by it too much. Rather, what they say is that "If you want to use a competing project, I won't stop you. It probably is good. It may be better in some respects. I like my own project and that's what I'm used to using and use."

This is by all means the right policy of "hyping" to adopt, if you want your project to be successful based on its own merits. Some projects compete for the same niche, without voicing too much hype against each other or for them, and this is a better indication that they are all healthy.

A Good Name

Finally, a project should have a good name. One example for a project with an awful name is CVSNT. There are two problems with the name:

It is based on CVS, which most people have ran into its limitations, is considered passé and unloved, and people would rather avoid.

The "NT" part implies it only runs on Windows-NT, which is both misleading and undesirable.

On the other hand, the competing project "Subversion" has a much better name, since it has nothing to do with CVS, or Windows NT, and since it is an English word and sounds cool.

Some projects are successful despite being badly named, while some have a very cool name, but languish. Still, a good name helps a lot.

Also consider what Linus Torvalds said about Linux and 386BSD (half jokingly):

No. That's it. The cool name, that is. We worked very hard on creating a name that would appeal to the majority of people, and it certainly paid off: thousands of people are using linux just to be able to say "OS/2? Hah. I've got Linux. What a cool name". 386BSD made the mistake of putting a lot of numbers and weird abbreviations into the name, and is scaring away a lot of people just because it sounds too technical.

Conclusion

Entire books (and web-sites) were filled with the various measures to achieve software quality, and what I described here was just a sample of it. The point is that these are not aspects of quality by themselves, but rather measures that help. None of them is a required or adequate condition for the success of a project, but the more are implemented the easier, faster, and more enjoying working on the project will be.

Prev  |   |  Next
Parameters of Quality  | Home |  Analysis of the Quality of the Various Freecell Solvers

What Makes Software High-Quality?
  |   |  Next

What Makes Software High-Quality?

Shlomi Fish

                        <shlomif@shlomifish.org>

Copyright © 2008 Shlomi Fish

This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 2.5 License (or at your option a greater version of it).

Revision History
Revision 1675 | 2007-04-02 | shlomif
Forked the template from a previous work and working on it.
Revision 1871 | 2008-05-04 | shlomif
Finalised the first draft. About to receive feedback.
Revision 1872 | 2008-05-04 | shlomif
Fixed many spelling/grammar/etc. problems, trailing whitespace, etc.
Revision 1882 | 2008-05-06 | shlomif
Fixed many spelling, grammar and syntax problems (thanks in part to Omer Zak). Added some bolds, and id=""'s, added the about section, reorganised the text a bit, and added the note about responsiveness and startup time.
Revision 1884 | 2008-05-06 | shlomif
Changed "a software" to something more idiomatic, and fixed a bad phrasing towards the beginning.

Table of Contents

Introduction
Parameters of Quality

The Program is Available for Downloading or Buying
The Version Number is Clearly Indicated
The Source is Available, Preferably under a Usable Licence
It "Just Works"
The Program has a Homepage
The Software is Easy to Compile, Deploy and Install
The Software Has Packages for Most Common Distributions
The Software Has Good, Extensive and Usable Documentation
Portability
Security
Backwards Compatibility
Good Ways to Provide Support
Speed and High Performance
Aesthetics
Conclusion

Ways to Achieve Quality

Having Modular, Well-Written Code
Automated Tests
Beta Testers
Frequency of Releases
Good Software Management
Good Social Engineering Skills
No Bad Politics
Good Communication Skills
Hype
A Good Name
Conclusion

Analysis of the Quality of the Various Freecell Solvers

Introduction
The Analysis Itself
Conclusion

About This Document

Copyrights
About the Author
Acknowledgements

Introduction

What is a high-quality software application? I'm not talking about the application that's the most hyped, or the fastest, most featureful, or best. You can often hear endless rants and Fear, Uncertainty and Doubt (FUD) attacks about it. Often, it has competing programs that are superior in many respects. But at the end of the day, it is one of the most popular programs out there and is what many people like to use, what they find as the right tool for the job, and often what they are told (or even forced) to use.

How did I think about it? I am active in the fc-solve-discuss mailing list, which is dedicated to computerised techniques for solving the Freecell solitaire card game, and for discussing other automated solving and research of Solitaire games. This mailing list was started after I wrote Freecell Solver (with a lowercase "c" and an uppercase "S"), an open-source solver, which has proven to be quite popular. However, this mailing list was not restricted to discussing it exclusively, and was joined by many other Freecell solving experts, researchers and enthusiasts.

Later on, I lost interest in Freecell Solver, and have only been fixing bugs in the latest stable version (2.8.x). Since it is open source, and with an aim to be a Bazaar-like project I welcome other people to take over and am willing to help them, but it is still very functional as it is.

Recently, this message was written by Gary Campbell, who wrote:

I think the solver discussion in the Wikipedia should mention that the FCPro solvers give quite lengthy and virtually unusable solutions. No human wants to follow the several hundred steps that usually result in order to get at what's really required to solve a given layout. If someone wants a solution that can be understood, they want one that is under 100 steps. This is a major contribution and it should be stated. There are a lot of "toy" solvers and only a very few of "industrial strength." One of the latter is the solver by Danny Jones. I don't see that on your list. The results he has gotten from his solver pretty much put your solver to shame. The more you hype Freecell Solver, the more criticism you open yourself up to.

Unfortunately, it's hard for me to determine what "industrial strength", "enterprise grade" and other such buzzwords are. But I'll try to define high quality here, and try to show when a program is high quality, and when it is not exactly the case.

I initially wanted to give some examples for software that I considered to be of exceptional high-quality, but I decided against it. That's because it is a matter of taste if this is the case for them, and since it may provoke too much criticism against this essay as a whole. Thus, I'll just give some examples, possibly accompanied by screenshots, of places where one program does something better than a different program, while not even implying that the latter is in fact lower-quality in all possible respects.

  |   |  Next
  |   |  Parameters of Quality